Please invite the Yan Dong envoy to the court
燕東の使者を宮殿に上らせてください
Greetings, Your Majesty
陛下にお目にかかる
Envoy, please rise
使者立ち上がってください
Your Majesty
陛下
For decades
数十年にわたって
Our Yan Dong court
私たち燕東朝堂
Has still held Xuan Kingdom's credentials
依然として宣国の符節を保持する
And considers itself a vassal state of Xuan
自己を宣朝の封国だと思っている
Now my father has sent me
今父が私を遣わせた
Hoping even more
さらに望む
To be able to
陛下とお会いできること
Restore our former friendship with Your Majesty
旧友と仲直りする
We are willing to offer ten thousand fine horses
私たちは万匹の良馬を捧げたい
To marry a princess
お姫様と結婚する
As queen
王后として
From then on
これ以降
With Great Xuan
大宣と
We will work together in harmony
心を合わせて協力する
Sharing the same spirit
同じ気
And connected branches
連枝
This proposal
この提案
I will consider it
私は考慮します
The Yan Dong envoy has come from afar
燕の東の使節が遠路はるばるやって来た
After a long journey
船と車での疲れ
Please
どうぞ
Return early to rest
早めに帰って休んだほうがいいよ
Thank you, Your Majesty
陛下ありがとうございます
Excellent
すごいです
Yan Dong
イードン
Is willing to help us attack Wuzhao
これは私たちがウーセイを攻めるために力を尽くすことをいとわないということです
But they want to marry a princess
でも彼らは王女と結婚したい
Isn't there only Princess Xunyang in the palace?
宮中には浔陽公主は一人しかいません
Right
はい
Just marry Princess Xunyang off to them
ただ浔陽公主を嫁がせればいい
Alright
よし
Let's discuss the next matter
次の件について話し合いましょう
Your Majesty
陛下
Lady Liu is still kneeling outside
劉昭儀はまだ外でひざまずいているよ
We can't persuade her to leave
説得しても行かないよ
Your Majesty
陛下
When you were in Yiyang, you promised Grandfather
あなたは弋陽にいたときおじいさんに約束しました
To protect me
臣女を守ってほしい
In peace and happiness for life
一生平安で喜びに満ちていますように
I want nothing
私は何もいりません
I beg you, don't let Yu'er leave
どうかユアーを行かせないでください
Rise first
先に起きる
Your Majesty
陛下
Don't let Yu'er leave
ユエルを離れさせないで
I beg you
お願いですご主人様
Listen to me
私の言うことを聞け
Return to the palace first
宮に戻る
Father
父上
Yan Dong has also been harassed by Wuzhao for years
燕東も常に邬伖の襲撃を受けている
Your son believes
私は思います
If the two states can form a marriage alliance
両国がもし秦と晋のような友好関係を結ぶことができれば
To watch over each other and together drive out Wuzhao
互いに助け合い共に険しきを越える
Would be the best strategy
これは最上の方法である
Sikong Sheng
シクウセイ
You're a coward
あなたは悪党です
That's your sister
それはあなたの妹です
How can you let her marry to a place like Yan Dong
どうして彼女を燕東みたいなところに嫁がせることができるの
A remote and poor place to suffer
辺鄙で貧しい土地で苦しむ
With Yan Dong's assistance
燕東の助けがあります
How many fewer of our people would die
我が国はどれだけ少ない人が亡くなるだろうか
To let my sister marry far away
妹を遠くに嫁がせる
How could I not be heartbroken
どうしてそれに心を痛めないことがあり得るでしょうか
But as members of the royal family
宗室にもなり得る
Why not bear the responsibility for the people
なぜ民衆の責任を背負わないのか
Do you think the people kneel to you
お前は民衆がなぜお前にひざまずくと思っているのか
Kneel to me
ひざまずけ
Kneel to Princess Xunyang
彼女浔陽公主に跪く
Father
父上
If the state and realm
若江の山と社稷
Must rely on Yu'er, a mere woman
阿钰という女性だけに頼るしかない
To bring stability and revival
安定と復興をもたらす
Then what use are all the men in court
それならこの満座の男たちは何のためにいるのか
Father
父上
Your son is willing to be the vanguard
私は先鋒として仕えたい
On the day of the northern expedition
来日北征
To defeat Wuzhao
殺破烏伖
Father's lifelong efforts
父上の半生の心血
Have all been for reviving Great Xuan
皆で大復興を宣言する
You are the father of all under heaven
この天下の君主であり父である
Should not be limited to one family
一つの家や姓にとらわれない
By personal affections
子女の情愛
All rise
みんな起きてください
I
朕
Will make my own decision
自主的な判断
Your Majesty
陛下
The Ministry of Rites just sent someone to ask again
礼部はちょうどまた人を遣わして尋ねさせた
Only a few days left before the envoy returns
使者が帰路につくまであと数日です
We must have an answer
何か答えを出さないといけないでしょう
Before
以前
I asked you to sound her out
私はあなたに遠回しに言わせた
To ask Xunyang's thoughts
浔阳の考えを聞いてみる
The princess cares for Your Majesty
お姫様は陛下を気の毒に思っている
This servant sees
使用人は見た
She is willing to go
行くつもりです
She said nothing else
他のことは言わなかった
This
これ
To leave home thousands of miles away
家を離れて万里
Sorrow is inevitable
悲しいのは仕方がない
But Princess Xunyang is filial
しかし浔陽の公主は孝行でした
She would never go against Your Majesty's wishes
決して陛下の御意に背くことはありません